Guide to the Leslie R. Wolfe papers RL.10994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leslie R. Wolfe papers
1972-2014 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Wolfe, Leslie R.
RL.10994
37.5 Linear Feet
During her career in women's public policy, Leslie R. Wolfe served as both the director of the Women's Educational Equity Act Program (WEEAP), and as the longtime director of the Center for Women Policy Studies. This collection documents her professional life and contains materials generated by her work with WEEAP, her speeches, women's health policy materials focusing on HIV/AIDS and human trafficking, and publications from the Center for Women Policy Studies.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Leslie R. Wolfe papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Biographical / Historical
Leslie R. Wolfe (1943-2017) spent her career advocating for women's equality through her public policy work in Washington, DC. Wolfe came to prominence as the director of the Women's Educational Equity Act Program (WEEAP), a government agency which fought against sex discrimination in eduation for women in the wake of Title IX. She next served as the director of the Center for Women Policy Studies (1987-2015), a feminist policy research institute. While there, Wolfe continuted to make significant contributions to the fight against gender discrimination in education by publishing a landmark study on gender and racial bias in the SAT test. She also made significant contributions to women's heath care policies through pioneering research and programming focused on women living with HIV/AIDS.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of materials documenting Leslie R. Wolfe's career in women's public policy, particularly her work as the director of the Women's Educational Equity Act Program from 1979-1987. These include lobbying materials, publications, speeches, grant administration, and correspondence. The collection also contains materials documenting Wolfe's work on women's health care policy from her time with the Center for Women Policy Studies, with an emphasis on HIV/AIDS and human trafficking. These materials include publications, conference proceedings, research reports, and correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
AIDS (Disease) in women -- United States; Sex discrimination in education -- United States; Women -- Government policy -- United States; Women's Health -- Legislation and jurisprudence; Women's health services -- Government policy -- United States; Wolfe, Leslie R.; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Women's Educational Equity Act Program (U.S.); Center for Women Policy Studies; United States. Education Amendments of 1972. Title IX
- Report of the Women's Action Program, 1972 (Box 1)
- A Look at Women in Education, 1972 (Box 1)
- Workshop, 1975 (Box 1)
- Women's Educational Equity Act (WEEA) Chronicles (part 1): Legislative Testimony, 1977 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 2): Evaluation Report, 1972 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 3): Legislative Recommendations, 1977 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 4): Dissemination Materials, 1976 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 5): FY Budget Materials, 1977 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 6): FY Budget Materials, 1976 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 7): FY Testimony, 1977 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 8): FY Testimony, 1976 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 9): Education Amendments, 1976 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 10): Proposed Spending Plan for 1976, 1975 (Box 1)
- WEEA Chronicles (part 11): Request for 1975 Budget Increase, 1974 (Box 1)
- First Annual Report, 1976 (Box 1)
- Women's Educational Equity Act: Comments, 1976 (Box 1)
- Taking Sexism Out of Education, 1977 (Box 1)
- Math Projects, 1976 (Box 2)
- 2nd Annual Report, 1977 (Box 2)
- Annual Report, 1978 (Box 2)
- New Specifications for WEEA, 1978 (Box 2)
- Federal Register, 1979 (Box 2)
- Survey of Women's Educational Equity Act Project Directors, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
- Commissioner's Reports, 1977 (Box 2)
- WEEA: Final Report, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
- WEEA: Program History and Development, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
- WEEA: Federal Register: Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
- WEEA: Legislative History (Box 2)
- WEEA: Act, 1994 (Box 2)
- WEEA: Title IX and Dissemination (Box 2)
- Dissemination Center for WEEA (Box 2)
- WEEA: General and State Grants, 1977-1979 (Box 2)
- Financial Planning, 1976-1979 (Box 2)
- Purchase Order Requests, 1979 (Box 3)
- An Agenda-Building Workshop for Black College and Women's Issues: Final Report, 1980 (Box 3)
- Sole Source Justification & Scope of Work: Demonstration Sites, 1980 (Box 3)
- Financial Planning, 1980 (Box 3)
- Department of Health, Education, and Welfare Projects, 1980 (Box 3)
- Grant Projects, 1980-1983 (Box 3)
- Women's Educational Equity Act Program (WEEAP) Reports, 1981 (Box 3)
- WEEAP: Project and Financial Planning, 1981 (Box 3)
- WEEAP: Annual Report, 1981 (Box 3)
- WEEAP: Annual Conference, 1981 (Box 3)
- Application for Grants Under Women's Educational Equity Act Program, 1981 (Box 3)
- WEEAP: National Advisory Council on Women's Educational Program, 1981 (Box 3)
- National Research Council, 1981 (Box 3)
- WEEAP: Rapid Feedback Evaluation, 1981 (Box 3)
- Notice of Proposed Annual Program Priorities, 1980 (Box 4)
- WEEAP: Project Directors Meeting, 1981 (Box 4)
- WEEA: Past, Present, and Future, 1981 (Box 4)
- Correspondence: Brent Marriot, 1982 (Box 4)
- Church Women United, Alabama Speech, 2010 (Box 5)
- AZ WPC Tuscon, 2008 (Box 5)
- EPA Women's History, 2008 (Box 5)
- Defense Logistics Agency Women's History Month, 2008 (Box 5)
- Women's Club of MN, 2008 (Box 5)
- Woman's Club of Minneapolis, 2008 (Box 5)
- Rotary Club, Minneapolis, 2008 (Box 5)
- UN Association, Minneapolis, 2008 (Box 5)
- Charleston, SC LWV, 2007 (Box 5)
- UC in DC, 2007 (Box 5)
- CT Press Conference, 2006 (Box 5)
- MCCFW Legislative Briefing/Trafficking, 2006 (Box 5)
- Coalition of Catholic Organizations Against Human Trafficking, 2006 (Box 5)
- St. Kate's Residency, 2006 (Box 5)
- MD Legislature, 2006 (Box 5)
- Women in Higher Education, 2006 (Box 5)
- Church Women United, Indianapolis, 2006 (Box 5)
- Ohio State/Clipping Our Wings, 2006 (Box 5)
- OSU: Mansfield, OH, 2006 (Box 5)
- ICE/DHS Seattle, 2005 (Box 6)
- AAVW Speech, 2005 (Box 6)
- LRW/WEEA, 1982 (Box 6)
- IPU, NYC, 2007 (Box 6)
- NCSC Sessions, 2007 (Box 6)
- Fairfax Commission for Women/Trafficking, 2006 (Box 6)
- Vital Voices, Russian Women, 2006 (Box 6)
- WEEA Article, Greenwood Press, 2006 (Box 6)
- Trafficking: Albequerque, NM, 2006; 2 folders (Box 6)
- Women of Diaspora: Velmanette Montgomery, 2007 (Box 7)
- DOL International, 2007 (Box 7)
- Fact Sheets: Trafficking, 2005 (Box 7)
- Women of NACO, 2007 (Box 7)
- Minnesota 2 Conference, 2003 (Box 7)
- Speech-PLEN Conference, 1997 (Box 7)
- Speech-Ford Foundation, 1994 (Box 7)
- Sen. Velmanette Montgomery, 2007 (Box 7)
- LWV Charleston, SC, 2007 (Box 7)
- DNC Women's Leadership Summit, Las Vegas, 2007 (Box 7)
- Sisters of St. Agnes, Fon du Lac, WI, 2007 (Box 7)
- WIIS Panel, 2007 (Box 7)
- Morella Class, 2012 (Box 7)
- Women's History Month, FDIC, 2012 (Box 7)
- Women's History Month, Ft. Belvoir, 2012 (Box 7)
- Trafficking: Sisters of Humility of Mary, Cleveland & Villa Maria, 2006 (Box 7)
- EPA Admin, 2008 (Box 7)
- Trafficking: MN Women's Club, 2008 (Box 7)
- LWV Kenyan Women, 2006 (Box 7)
- Loyola College, Baltimore, 2006 (Box 7)
- Lab for New Thinking on Foreign Policy, Boston, 2006 (Box 7)
- Des Moines and Davenport, 2006 (Box 7)
- Good Shepherd Sisters, Tarrytown Trafficking, 2006 (Box 7)
- Grand Forts, ND and Minn/St. Paul Trafficking, 2006 (Box 7)
- AAVW/NCNW Reston, VA, 2006 (Box 7)
- DOL International Programs Grantees, 2007 (Box 8)
- CT AAVW Bridgeport USPACT, 2007 (Box 8)
- WEEA Interview, 2007 (Box 8)
- MLWPC Political Skills Campaign School, Louisville, KY, 2007 (Box 8)
- Report of the Summit on Girls and Violence, 1998 (Box 8)
- The Politics of Reproductions in the 1990s: Contraceptive and Reproductive Technologies, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
- The Law and Pregnancy: Protection or Punishment?, 1987-1990; 2 folders (Box 8)
- The Guide to Resources on Women and AIDS, 1992; 2 folders (Box 9)
- State Legislators Action Kit: Women and HIV/AIDS, 1997 (Box 9)
- Strong Proud Sisters: Girls and Young Women with Disabilities, 2001 (Box 9)
- Center for Women Policy Studies, 2001-2007 (Box 9)
- New Frontiers for Worker-Friendly Companies, 1996 (Box 9)
- Fighting for Our Lives: Women Confronting AIDS, 1990-1998 (Box 9)
- Mandatory HIV Testing of Pregnant Women, 1997 (Box 10)
- Midlife/Older Women and HIV/AIDS, 1994 (Box 10)
- Report of the Symposium on Multiethnic Feminist Visions of Fatherhood, 1999 (Box 10)
- HIV and Drug Policies: Women's Reproductive Rights Under Attack, 2000 (Box 10)
- Women Engaging Globally, 2004 (Box 10)
- The Metro Collaborative for Women Living with HIV/AIDS: Telling the Story, 1999 (Box 10)
- Inaccessible Miracles? Women's Access to HIV/AIDS Medications, 1999 (Box 10)
- Violence Against Women, 2001 (Box 10)
- News from the Center for Women Policy Studies, 2002-2007; 2 folders (Box 10)
- Building a Women-Focused Response to AIDS, 1999 (Box 11)
- The Report of the Teen Women Leadership Development Initiative Survey, 2001 (Box 11)
- Poverty to Self-Sufficiency, 2003-2004 (Box 11)
- Clipping Our Wings, 2001 (Box 11)
- The SAT Gender Gap, 1989 (Box 11)
- gTIP South Asia, 2010 (Box 11)
- CGP 2013-2015 Budget/Concept Paper, 2012 (Box 11)
- Women's Educational Equity Act Program, 1980-1983 (Box 11)
- Report of the National Women of Color Work/Life Survey, 1999 (Box 11)
- NACWEP, 1980-1983 (Box 11)
- Correspondence Re: Department of Elementary and Secondary Education, 1982 (Box 12)
- Correspondence as Director of Women's Educational Equity Act Program, 1982-1983 (Box 12)
- Fact Sheet: Attack on WEEAP, 1982 (Box 12)
- Regional Educational Equity Awareness Conference, 1982 (Box 12)
- FY Continuations, 1982 (Box 12)
- Administrative Procedures, 1982 (Box 12)
- WEEAP Grant Application Committee, 1982 (Box 12)
- FY 82 Field Reader Invites, 1982 (Box 12)
- WEEA Grant Decisions, 1982 (Box 12)
- LW Testimony: Original: Summary, 1983 (Box 12)
- Reagan Administration Attack on Educational Equity for Women and Minorities, 1981-1983 (Box 12)
- Oversight Hearing on Department of Education's Reorganization and Reduction-in-force, 1983 (Box 12)
- Field Readers: Master Lists, 1982 (Box 12)
- LW Speech for Benish, 1982 (Box 13)
- Speech for D. Jean Benish, 1982 (Box 13)
- National Commission on Working Women, 1982 (Box 13)
- WEEA Project Directors' Conference (general), 1982 (Box 13)
- WEEA Project Directors' Conference (Vicki Jackson), 1982 (Box 13)
- WEEA Project Directors' Conference (Leslie Wolfe), 1982 (Box 13)
- WEEAP Project Directors' Conference, 1981; 2 folders (Box 13)
- Letters of Support for WEEA, 1981; 2 folders (Box 13)
- Slate (final/signed), 1981 (Box 13)
- WEEA Annual Report, 1982 (Box 13)
- Office of the Special Counsel, 1982 (Box 14)
- MSPB Complaint, 1982; 2 folders (Box 14)
- Department of Education RIF and Reorganization, 1983-1987 (Box 14)
- Magazine Articles Re: WEEA, 1983-1984 (Box 14)
- Dept. of Education, 1983 (Box 14)
- Dept. of Education Reorganization (Box 14)
- Benish Response to LW Support Letters, 1982 (Box 14)
- Memos to Benish from DUSM, ASLPA, 1982 (Box 14)
- RIF, 1982 (Box 14)
- Allegation of Prohibited Personnel Action by the Department of Education, 1982 (Box 14)
- Detail, 1982 (Box 14)
- RIF/Reorganization, 1983 (Box 14)
- Conservative Caucus FOIA, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
- Memos from OESEI to OESE, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
- Annotated List of Field Readers, 1982 (Box 15)
- LW Memos to Staff, 1982 (Box 15)
- Newspaper Articles, 1982-1983 (Box 15)
- Final Letter to WEEA Grantees, 1983 (Box 15)
- Field Readers, 1982; 2 folders (Box 15)
- Article for APSA: News for Teachers of Political Science and PS, 1982 (Box 15)
- Memos from Asst. Secretary for Elementary and Secondary Education, 1982 (Box 15)
- LW: Letters to Congress re: Complaint, 1982 (Box 15)
- RIF Final, 1983 (Box 15)
- Grievant File: Leslie Wolfe, 1983 (Box 15)
- Proposal to Develop and Operate a WEEA Program Publishing Center, 1984 (Box 16)
- Implementing Institutional Self-Evaluation (Box 16)
- Business and Management Training for Rural Women, 1979 (Box 16)
- WEEAP Evaluation Handbook, 1978 (Box 16)
- Additional Training Aids (Box 16)
- And Then What Happened?, 1983 (Box 16)
- Bill of Rights in Action, 1983 (Box 16)
- Implementing Title IX and Attaining Sex Equity: Teacher Educator's Role (Box 16)
- Issues of Sex Bias and Sex Fairness in Career Interest Measurement, 1975 (Box 16)
- Implementing Title IX and Attaining Sex Equity: Physical Activity Specialist's Role (Box 16)
- WEECN Resources in Women's Educational Equity, 1980 (Box 17)
- Disadvantaged Women and their Children, 1983 (Box 17)
- WEEAP Literature, 1981-1982 (Box 17)
- Women's Educational Equity Communications Network, 1980; 2 folders (Box 17)
- Building Instruction around Sex Equity (Box 17)
- Competitive Athletics: In Search of Equal Opportunity, 1976 (Box 17)
- Title IX Information Materials, 1976 (Box 18)
- The Catalyst Training Package: Increasing Options for Rural Youth, 1982 (Box 18)
- Sources of Measures of Women's Educational Equity, 1979 (Box 18)
- Implementing Title IX: A Sample Workshop, 1976 (Box 18)
- Global Power Ambassador Letters, 2010 (Box 18)
- Agenda for Accelerated Country Action for Women, Girls, Gender Equality, HIV, 2010 (Box 19)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Reproductive Rights, 2011-2012 (Box 19)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Clearinghouse, 2008 (Box 19)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Women and HIV/AIDS, 2011 (Box 19)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Miscellaneous, 2006-2012 (Box 19)
- Center for Women Policy Studies Publications, 2001 (Box 19)
- Issues, Policies, and Programs for Midlife/Older Women, 1982 (Box 20)
- Women with HIV/AIDS Speak Out: The Maryland Report, 1998 (Box 20)
- Earnings Sharing in Social Security: Model for Reform, 1998 (Box 20)
- Women with HIV/AIDS, 1992-1996 (Box 20)
- Metro DC Collaborative for Women with HIV/AIDS and the HIV Community Coalition, 1996 (Box 20)
- Congressional Briefing on Girls and Young Women with Disabilities, 2002 (Box 20)
- Victims No More: Girls Fight Back Against Male Violence, 1997 (Box 20)
- Building a National Policy Agenda: 10 Principles for Women-Focused HIV/AIDS Prevention, 1996 (Box 20)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Expert Planning Committee - April/September 1996 (Box 21)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Violence and Disabled Women, 1991-2001 (Box 21)
- Partnership of Women Elected/Appointed Representatives, 2007 (Box 21)
- Briefing Memorandum: Immigration and Refugee Law Affecting Trafficked Persons, 2005 (Box 21)
- E-NEWS from the Center for Women Policy Studies - November 2010-October 2012, 2009-2012; 2 folders (Box 21)
- Board of Directors, 2008 (Box 21)
- Women's Equality: An Unfinished Business, 1995-2000 (Box 21)
- National Women of Color Organizations, 1991 (Box 21)
- Welfare to Wages, 1998 (Box 21)
- Sourcebook of Measures of Women's Educational Equity, 1982 (Box 21)
- Bylaws (original) (Box 21)
- Global Power Sample Packet, 2010 (Box 21)
- Sourcebook of Measures of Women's Educational Equity, 1982 (Box 22)
- AIDSTAR/UNDP, 2012 (Box 22)
- Department of Justice, 2010 (Box 22)
- Grant Funder File: Libra Foundation: PEAC/Policy Boot Camp, 2008 (Box 22)
- Gale Group: Royalties, 2012 (Box 22)
- Global Power Caribbean, 2011-2012 (Box 22)
- Global Power: Report of the First Two Years, 2006-2007 (Box 22)
- The Center for Women Policy Studies at 25, 1997 (Box 22)
- Global Power Packet Template Exact Contents, 2010 (Box 22)
- Medicaid Managed Care: Serving Women with HIV/AIDS, 1996 (Box 23)
- Women and HIV/AIDS, 1999 (Box 23)
- Women, Pregnancy, and Substance Abuse, 1991 (Box 23)
- Global Power Research Report, 2006 (Box 23)
- What Will Dubya Do?, 2001 (Box 23)
- MAC AIDS Fund, 2009-2010 (Box 24)
- State Trafficking Laws, 2012 (Box 24)
- Foundation for a Just Society, 2012 (Box 24)
- Libra Grant, 2011 (Box 24)
- Center for Women Policy Studies: Pacific Rim Program, 2012-2013 (Box 24)
- Center for Global Partnership, Pacific Rim Program, 2013 (Box 24)
- Earmark, 2007 (Box 24)
- Poverty Viewed as a Woman's Problem: The US Case, 1982 (Box 24)
- Getting Civilized, 1994 (Box 24)
- Leslie R. Wolfe Resume (Box 24)
- Multidisciplinary Intellectual Exchange: Final Report, 2012 (Box 24)
- The Impact of Women's Political Leadership on Democracy and Development, 2013 (Box 24)
- Center for Global Partnership, Pacific Rim Program, 2012-2013 (Box 25)
- Center for Global Partnership, Grant for Pacific Rim Program, 2010-2011 (Box 25)
- Trafficking Women, 2005-2007 (Box 25)
- Workplace Cultures: A Reality Check, 1995 (Box 25)
- Post Election Action Convening for Women State Legislators, 2012 (Box 25)
- Women-Focused Response to HIV/AIDS (Box 25)
- Program Plans, 2000-2004 (Box 25)
- Foreign Policy Institute for State Legislators, 2006 (Box 25)
- Project Empower for PSE, 2013 (Box 25)
- Trafficking Women, 2005-2014 (Box 25)
- The Contract with Women of the USA State Legislators Initiative, 2011 (Box 25)
- Archives, 1975-1983 (Box 25)